<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://brettbim.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://brettbim.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-03-30T12:22:51+00:00</updated><id>http://brettbim.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Brett Bim</title><subtitle>&quot;I write to discover what I believe&quot;</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Gus Engling Deer Hunt 2023</title><link href="http://brettbim.com/hunting/outdoors/2024/01/20/gus-engling-deer-hunt.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gus Engling Deer Hunt 2023" /><published>2024-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://brettbim.com/hunting/outdoors/2024/01/20/gus-engling-deer-hunt</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://brettbim.com/hunting/outdoors/2024/01/20/gus-engling-deer-hunt.html"><![CDATA[<p>My entries into the Texas Parks and Wildlife draw hunt season won me four hunts in 2023-2024.  The first of these was the last hunt of the season at <a href="https://tpwd.texas.gov/huntwild/hunt/public/public_hunt_drawing/hunt-category-details.phtml?OCat=GDA#EN">Gus Engeling WMA</a> near Palestine.  The dates were December 12-14 and this was hunt six of six on the property for the year not including youth hunts.  So while I was excited to go, my expectations were low.  Public deer hunts are hard by definition and when the woods have been full of hunters for a couple of months, they are even harder.</p>

<p>I went down Monday, December 11th to camp overnight so that I didn’t have to worry about being on time for registration and orientation.  Gus Engeling WMA is one of the best I’ve been to in regards to infrastructure.  They have good roads throughout and a good campsite on Highway 287 with level pads for RVs, a bathroom and water available in a central location.  I was the only one who showed up Monday so I got my pick of the sites.</p>

<p>Tuesday morning, I got up for a walk to the conservation center.  It’s always a slight shock to the system to be in the woods after a long time in the modern world.  The birds, the air, the open space above your head, all contribute to a sense of disarray until you get used to the sensation of it again.  All the gates were closed so the walk was a short one.  They have several informational signs throughout the WMA that provide information on the conservation activities that go on there like strip clearing and management hunts.</p>

<p>At registration, it looked like a full hunt.  As usual, it was almost entirely men.  There were two boys under the age of 10 with their fathers and that was great to see.  You are given the option to choose some compartments that you would prefer.  However, since I had never been to this WMA and there was no scouting allowed, I let the biologists pick my compartment.  Gus Engeling is a large WMA, over 11,000 acres so the chance of randomly picking a good compartment was low.  I ended up in compartment 3.  Orientation was mostly about safety and process.  This was an antlerless/spike hunt but the head biologist was pretty clear he’d prefer we didn’t shoot any spikes.  At 12:30 or so, we were sent out to our compartments.</p>

<p>One of the many hard parts about these hunts is you show up one day and are handed a section of land that could be 200-500 acres.  Figuring out what to do with that size property in a couple of hours isn’t easy.  I had brought both a climbing stand and a popup.  I started out with my climber as the biologist that gave me information about the compartment said that was probably the best option.  However, I never found a location with a tree straight enough and no lower limbs that I thought was good.  Tuesday night I found a spot on a clearing with quite a bit of deer and hog sign that I thought would be good for the popup so I went back to the truck to get it.  Unfortunately, it broke as I was trying to put it up.  So I just tucked a chair back into a cedar bush with the idea that I’d hunt there in the morning hoping anything would enter the clearing from the opposite side of where I would be sitting.</p>

<p>I returned to the truck and took the climber on a long hike to the far east end of the compartment.  There, I again found a lot of sign, especially of hogs and territory that looked great.  However, none of the trees surrounding the area were at all suitable for a climbing stand.  Frustrated at this point, I put out some corn and scent and propped up against the base of a cedar tree with very low expecations.</p>

<p>About 4:00 PM, I heard a pretty solid rustling sound 75 yards behind me.  Turning around, three or four yearling pigs moving along the edge of the clearing towards me.  Before I could get turned around with the gun, they had moved back into the woods.  However, they hadn’t smelled me and I heard the sounder moving just off to my north in the oak leaves.  There was a large briar thicket between their position and me.  I decided the only chance I had was to belly crawl east with the hopes they’d come out of the woods near the edge of the clearing and a fire lane.</p>

<p>Surprisingly, this is exactly what happened.  After crawling about 50 yards, I laid down in the middle of the clearing and 5 minutes later, the sounder appeared directly in front of me about 40 yards away.  This was so surprising that I was completely unprepared.  My experience with large game hunting is that unless you’re at a corn feeder, they don’t tend to stick around long.  Laying prone on the ground, heart beating out of my chest, I didn’t have a good position to really see their behavior.  The piglets and yearlings were running around a lot which added further distraction.  I finally picked a large white hog.  However, in my rush, I didn’t consider range or take time to calm down.  When I pulled the trigger, I’m fairly sure I jerked on the gun.  The sounder scattered and ran off south.  I waited about about five minutes knowing I’d made a poor shot.</p>

<p>Searching for a blood trail produced nothing.  I walked increasingly larger circles around the area where I thought the hog was and found no evidence of any blood.  In the end, I resigned myself to the evidence that I’d made a terrible shot from 40 yards and completely missed the target.  With little chance of something else showing up at that point, I sat under a tree until last light and made the long, empty handed walk back to the truck.</p>

<p>Wednesday morning, I hunted from the chair I’d set up in the clearing.  I got there in the dark about 5:30 and settled in for the sun to rise.  While there were lots of birds singing and flitting about, little else happened for most of the morning.  About 10:30, a decent six point buck walked around the same corner where I had walked in and we both shocked each other as we made eye contact at the same time.  He immediately bounded off and wasn’t legal for this hunt anyway.</p>

<p>My compartment had a raised box blind in it over a feeder that was used during youth hunts.  With a broke popup and not much luck finding a good place to use my climbing stand, I resigned myself to hunt from the blind both Wednesday night and Thursday morning, knowing the odds of something coming through was minimal.  I did put out quite a bit of corn around the feeder and sat there from 2-6 on Wednesday and 5:30-</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Hunting" /><category term="Outdoors" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My entries into the Texas Parks and Wildlife draw hunt season won me four hunts in 2023-2024. The first of these was the last hunt of the season at Gus Engeling WMA near Palestine. The dates were December 12-14 and this was hunt six of six on the property for the year not including youth hunts. So while I was excited to go, my expectations were low. Public deer hunts are hard by definition and when the woods have been full of hunters for a couple of months, they are even harder.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building AWS Route53 Resolver Outbound Endpoints with Terraform</title><link href="http://brettbim.com/technology/2023/09/11/aws-route53-outbound-endpoint.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building AWS Route53 Resolver Outbound Endpoints with Terraform" /><published>2023-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://brettbim.com/technology/2023/09/11/aws-route53-outbound-endpoint</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://brettbim.com/technology/2023/09/11/aws-route53-outbound-endpoint.html"><![CDATA[<p>At work, we are moving out of an legacy data center to AWS.  Our initial stab at that has been to stand up a staging environment that clients can use to verify changes.  Currently, we have several Docker Swarms that run different services.  These services use <a href="https://traefik.io/">Traefik</a> as an application gateway to route requests from client applications.  To facilitate this, we need URLs for particular sections of our application stack like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">preprod-dmz.example.com</code>.</p>

<p>Normally, in a purely cloud environment, this would be straightforward.  We’d set up a hosted zone and utilize Route53 to create and manage these zones.  However, DNS is not something we migrating immediately and we still wanted to use <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-server/identity/ad-ds/plan/dns-and-ad-ds">Active Directory</a> to manage our DNS.  We needed a way for the EC2 instances that host the Docker Swarms to be able to resolve DNS in our on-prem domain controllers.  We explored two options, Private Hosted Zones and AWS Route53 Resolver endpoints.  In the end, the latter seemed the easiest to set up.</p>

<p>This post details how we went about setting this up.  As always, the AWS documentation seemed to be missing a few critical pieces for a real world app that bit us but overall, this was a pretty easy process.  We use Terragrunt and Terraform to provision infrastructure.</p>

<p>One thing to note: these nodes are not currently on our domain which is why we’re going this direction.  Obviously, if we joined them to the domain, DNS resolution would probably be a trivial matter.  However in the short term, we have not done that as we expect to migrate away from Docker Swarm to managed services in AWS.</p>

<p>AWS Route53 Resolver has two ways to manage DNS queries: Inbound and Outbound endpoints.  The former is used to send DNS queries from your on-prem network to DNS resolvers in AWS.  The latter is the opposite.  For now, we only have a use case for Outbound, e.g. sending DNS queries in the Swarms to our on-prem domain controllers.</p>

<div class="language-terraform highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">module</span> <span class="s2">"resolver_sg"</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nx">source</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s2">"./security_group"</span>

  <span class="nx">name</span>         <span class="p">=</span> <span class="kd">var</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">name</span>
  <span class="nx">description</span>  <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s2">"Security group for forwarding endpoints in AWS Resolver"</span>
  <span class="nx">vpc_id</span>       <span class="p">=</span> <span class="kd">var</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">vpc_id</span>
  <span class="nx">tags</span>         <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nx">merge</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">local</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">tags</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="nx">Name</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="kd">var</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">name</span> <span class="p">})</span>
  <span class="nx">egress_rules</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="kd">var</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">egress_rules</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>First, we need a security group.  This is where the one gotcha that we ran into lies.  Intuitively, and in the AWS docs, for an Outbound Endpoint, you’d assume you needed an Egress Rule of tcp(DNS) on port 53.  However, this assumption would be wrong.  More on that to follow.</p>

<div class="language-terraform highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">resource</span> <span class="s2">"aws_route53_resolver_endpoint"</span> <span class="s2">"endpoint"</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nx">name</span>               <span class="p">=</span> <span class="kd">var</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">name</span>
  <span class="nx">direction</span>          <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s2">"OUTBOUND"</span>
  <span class="nx">security_group_ids</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="k">module</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">resolver_sg</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">security_group</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">id</span><span class="p">]</span>

  <span class="nx">dynamic</span> <span class="s2">"ip_address"</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nx">for_each</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="kd">var</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">domains</span>

    <span class="nx">content</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nx">subnet_id</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nx">ip_address</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">value</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">subnet_id</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>

  <span class="nx">tags</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="kd">local</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">tags</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Next, you need the endpoint definition.  In this case, it’s an OUTBOUND endpoint.  We build the ip_address section dynamically based on how many domains are passed in.</p>

<div class="language-terraform highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">resource</span> <span class="s2">"aws_route53_resolver_rule"</span> <span class="s2">"rule"</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nx">for_each</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="kd">var</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">domains</span>

  <span class="nx">domain_name</span>          <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nx">each</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">value</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">domain_name</span>
  <span class="nx">rule_type</span>            <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s2">"FORWARD"</span>
  <span class="nx">name</span>                 <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nx">each</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">key</span>
  <span class="nx">resolver_endpoint_id</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nx">aws_route53_resolver_endpoint</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">endpoint</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">id</span>
  <span class="nx">target_ip</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nx">ip</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="kd">var</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">domain_controller_ip</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>

  <span class="nx">tags</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="kd">local</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">tags</span>

<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="k">resource</span> <span class="s2">"aws_route53_resolver_rule_association"</span> <span class="s2">"assoc"</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nx">for_each</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nx">aws_route53_resolver_rule</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">rule</span>

  <span class="nx">resolver_rule_id</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nx">each</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">value</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">id</span>
  <span class="nx">vpc_id</span>           <span class="p">=</span> <span class="kd">var</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">vpc_id</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Finally we build the rules that the Resolver uses to know to forward queries based on the domains.  The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">target_ip</code> is our domain controller for this environment.</p>

<p>When this Terraform was executed, it seemed to properly set up the required infrastructure.  First glance at a domain in the zone resolved the URL properly.  However, upon further examination, lots of the queries were timing out and returning a SERVFAIL when using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">dig</code>.</p>

<p>To diagnose the problem, we turned on <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/Route53/latest/DeveloperGuide/resolver-query-logs.html">Resolver Query Logging</a>.  This made the problem immediately apparent when logs like this started coming through:</p>

<div class="language-json highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="nl">"version"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"1.100000"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="nl">"account_id"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"111111111"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="nl">"region"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"us-west-2"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="nl">"vpc_id"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"vpc-thevpc"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="nl">"query_timestamp"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"2023-09-11T19:01:45Z"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="nl">"query_name"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"preprod-dmz.example.com."</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="nl">"query_type"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"A"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="nl">"query_class"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"IN"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="nl">"rcode"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"SERVFAIL"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="nl">"answers"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[],</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="nl">"srcaddr"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"10.100.51.140"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="nl">"srcport"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"38214"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="nl">"transport"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"UDP"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="nl">"srcids"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
         </span><span class="nl">"instance"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"i-someinstanceid"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
         </span><span class="nl">"resolver_endpoint"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"rslvr-out-resolverid"</span><span class="w">
     </span><span class="p">}</span><span class="w">
 </span><span class="p">}</span><span class="w">
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p>These queries are coming across UDP and so only having Egress Rules on the security group for port 53 and TCP was clearly not going to work.  We added the UDP ports in our Terragrunt along with a CIDR restriction of our internal network and suddenly, the DNS resolution started happening on the Outbound Endpoints.</p>

<p>Overall, this was an easy setup with only the one gotcha.  We now have URLs successfully resolving in Docker Swarm on EC2 instances by forwarding specific queries to our own prem domain controller.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At work, we are moving out of an legacy data center to AWS. Our initial stab at that has been to stand up a staging environment that clients can use to verify changes. Currently, we have several Docker Swarms that run different services. These services use Traefik as an application gateway to route requests from client applications. To facilitate this, we need URLs for particular sections of our application stack like preprod-dmz.example.com.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Migrating From Wordpress to Jekyll</title><link href="http://brettbim.com/technology/2023/06/13/wordpress-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Migrating From Wordpress to Jekyll" /><published>2023-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://brettbim.com/technology/2023/06/13/wordpress-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://brettbim.com/technology/2023/06/13/wordpress-to-jekyll.html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been a Wordpress user for about as long as I have been writing online.  I have blog posts going back at least to 2005.  I have always enjoyed Wordpress much to the chargrin of my more technically hip friends.  But the platform is easy to setup, easy to find hosting for and in recent years, easy to self-host on AWS with Lightsail.</p>

<p>The plugin architecture of Wordpress means there is always a plugin for something you need to do, whether it’s email newsletter subscriptions or large exports or SEO.  If you use a hosting Platform like Wordpress.com or other popular site, the setup and maintenance over time is pretty straightforward.  You pay a little more for that but it’s worth it for non-technical people.  In recent years, I’ve self-hosted both on Azure and AWS.  Neither of these was terribly difficult to get goin if you have experience in the web and came with a cheaper monthly price tag.</p>

<p>Azure was free because I had MSDN credits through a previous company.  AWS cost about $8 a month on Lightsail.  The downsides of this cost savings was ease of updates.  The updating of Wordpress itself and the plugins remained the same, just a step you could do through the interface.  However, updating the underlying infrastructure like PHP was much less user-friendly.  In my case, using a Bitnami provided image on Lightsail meant I had to update the entire setup.  As I’ve gotten older and taken on other hobbies (and responsibilities like entertaining a 6 year old), updating Lightsail images took a very serious back seat on the TODO list.</p>

<p>So recently, during a bout of activity reduction, I decided to explore other hosting options.  <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/">Jekyll</a> hosted on <a href="https://pages.github.com/">Github Pages</a> quickly rose to the top because I’m familiar with Ruby should I ever need to do anything beyond writing Markdown and for a site like mine is completely free.  I don’t have any dynamic content, just 18 years of blathering on about things that catch my fancy.</p>

<p>Setting up Jekyll was easy for anyone comfortable with Github.  I had a basic blog in about an hour.  I then found a theme I liked, <a href="https://mmistakes.github.io/minimal-mistakes/docs/quick-start-guide/">Minimal Mistakes</a> which has things like post archives and a nice splash screen for the home page.  Implementing it took about another day, with off and on work.  The final step was to try and get an import of my Wordpress content without too much difficulty.</p>

<p>Luckily, because the Wordpress community is pretty awesome, there is a <a href="https://github.com/benbalter/wordpress-to-jekyll-exporter">good plugin</a> for exporting Wordpress content out to Markdown files in the structure expected by Jekyll.  In theory you can install the plugin and then just do the export from the UI.  However, I ran into problems with this approach where the export would never succeed.  I anticipate it’s because I was on an older version of both PHP and Wordpress than maybe it supported.  There was also a mention in the issues list about a large site timing out.  Luckily, that same issue mentioned the CLI.  The developer of the plugin had actually built a CLI for the tool which is amazing.</p>

<p>I connected to my Lightsail instance and found the location where the plugin had been installed by Wordpress.  Sure enough, there was the CLI which you can execute directly on the command line.  This resulted in a zip file of all content going back 18 years from my site.  I copied that off the instance, unpacked it locally and began bringing over essays.  At first, I just did one at a time to try and figure out the pattern necessary for updating the Jekyll metadata.  That quickly revealed the necessary things that had to change and I did a quick Find and Replace on the entire archive, copied them into the right spot, published it to Github and the site was live.</p>

<p>I anticipate that any essays from Wordpress that had links or images are probably broken but for now, just having the content was what I wanted.  This enabled me to delete the Lightsail instance, saving ~$8 a month.  Overall the process was quite easy and I’m looking forward to sporadically posting with Jekyll without having to constantly worry about the maintenance and upkeep of Wordpress and PHP.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been a Wordpress user for about as long as I have been writing online. I have blog posts going back at least to 2005. I have always enjoyed Wordpress much to the chargrin of my more technically hip friends. But the platform is easy to setup, easy to find hosting for and in recent years, easy to self-host on AWS with Lightsail.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thoughts from Rivercliff, Lakeview AR</title><link href="http://brettbim.com/travel/2023/05/28/lakeview-arkansas-rivercliff.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts from Rivercliff, Lakeview AR" /><published>2023-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://brettbim.com/travel/2023/05/28/lakeview-arkansas-rivercliff</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://brettbim.com/travel/2023/05/28/lakeview-arkansas-rivercliff.html"><![CDATA[<p>This was supposed to be the annual fishing trip with Dad.  Every year, for the past 20 or so, we’ve taken a trip to Arkansas to trout fish and play golf, often with David McCaskill who was an an old friend of Dad’s and mine.  David passed away last year so we made the trip in 2022 with the whole family.  This year though, it was going to be just Dad and I again.  Unfortunately, he got the flu this week.</p>

<p>So, late in the game with a paid for cabin and no travel insurance, plans changed for the fishing trip.  Mara is out of school and the kid had one last day of kindergarten we figured she could miss.  So we piled into the truck with a load of stuff and a new three month old puppy for the seven hour plus drive to Lakeview, AR.  In the past, we’d stayed at Stetson’s on the White which is a really nice lodge type place with a really nice price tag to go along with it.  Last year, we booked a home through VRBO on the river which was really nice and not any less expensive than Stetson’s.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, when I booked the place a month ago for Memorial Day weekend, pickings were pretty thin already.  Stetson’s may have had availability but this year, I didn’t want to spend that kind of money.  Luckily, I found <a href="https://rivercliff.com/">Rivercliff</a> which is a small outfit with four cabins on the White River east of the state park.</p>

<p>The economy of the White River tourism industry is in many ways a clash of a nostalgic past and a more consumerist future.  There are plenty of newer homes listed on VRBO and others with four or more bedrooms, granite countertops, outdoor fireplaces and the works.  Of course, it’s nice to stay in these sorts of places.  However, they come with $300 a night price tags which for a four night guys fishing trip can add up fast for amenities that might not be fully appreciated.</p>

<p>On the other end of the spectrum are places like Rivercliff.  The cabins here were probably built in the last century.  They have beds in the living area.  They have one small bathroom.  They have stoves that may be older than I am.  In today’s consumerist economy, they are certainly outdated and have lots of rough edges like the fridge door only opening a third of the way because when they buit the kitchen 40 years ago, fridges were a great deal smaller.</p>

<p>Yet, from the substantial deck, the birdsong is still as vibrant as it is at places twice as expensive.  The owner here has gone out of the way to encourage birds, installing several purple martin houses which are filled to be brim along with feeders on every deck.  We saw deer out the kitchen window yesterday morning and again just now, drawn in by a salt lick the owner must have placed for just such occastions.  The river still flows along just as peacefully as anywhere else.</p>

<p>Yesterday, as I fished by the river, H fished some (until her patience and attention ran out), waded into a 45 degree river up to her chest, watched a baby bird fall out of its nest several days too early for its fledgling flight, construct an elaborate home out of rocks, leaves and sticks for the dandelions she’d picked, held a three pound brown trout I’d managed to catch, watched her dog try to eat that baby bird, and splashed her unwilling mama with that 45 degree water.  The day before, we went to Bull Shoals Caverns, a place more reminiscent of my childhood in age and experience, than her’s.  We bought cookies from the Bull Shoals First Baptist Bake Sale which had set up in front of Harp’s.</p>

<p>These are things few kids (or adults for that matter) get now, on vacation or otherwise.  In a world of digital entertainment, this is all so insufferably slow.  An experience of nature, a feeling of community, the slower, more rough but more rewarding types of entertainment.  We’ll wonder if the baby bird made it (managed to save it somehow from the puppy but its odds seem slim).  H will ask if we’ll have trout for dinner (so far I’ve been reticent to clean fish which is probably another interesting line of thinking to explore related to the American Consumer).</p>

<p>It is slower here, something I increasingly find both difficult to adjust to and despately needing.  It is harder and harder to put the phone away or even down momentarily.  But this type of vacation, with beautiful outdoors, birdsong and frankly, terrible internet and cell coverage, almost demands it.  I’m nostalgic at times like these for the vacations I took as a kid.  We didn’t travel often but when we did, it was to places like this, rustic cabins on rivers or lakes or at family reunions where you still mostly cooked your own meals and were entertained as much by contingency as anything else.  A random trip to a caverns because there was a 40 year old sign beside of the road.  An outdoor life museum because someone left a flyer in the cabin at some point.  There were no plans.  And from that lack of plans comes memories of cold trips across lakes to fish or telling the game warden that no, in fact my dad and his friend had caught four fish in the lake we weren’t supposed to be fishing in, not one small one.</p>

<p>Today we have to get up and drive the seven hours back to Texas.  I’m already missing the river and the birds and the cold mornings.  I’m ready to return to something far away from computers.  But I’m thankful for the time with my family at a rustic cabin on a river I love and cherish each moment like that I get.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Travel" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was supposed to be the annual fishing trip with Dad. Every year, for the past 20 or so, we’ve taken a trip to Arkansas to trout fish and play golf, often with David McCaskill who was an an old friend of Dad’s and mine. David passed away last year so we made the trip in 2022 with the whole family. This year though, it was going to be just Dad and I again. Unfortunately, he got the flu this week.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lightsail, Bitnami and SSH</title><link href="http://brettbim.com/technology/2022/01/28/lightsail-bitnami-and-ssh.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lightsail, Bitnami and SSH" /><published>2022-01-28T14:25:28+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-28T14:25:28+00:00</updated><id>http://brettbim.com/technology/2022/01/28/lightsail-bitnami-and-ssh</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://brettbim.com/technology/2022/01/28/lightsail-bitnami-and-ssh.html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog runs in Lightsail on WordPress with a Certified by Bitnami instance. Lately, I’ve run into the following when trying to ssh in from the Lightsail console:</p>

<figure class="wp-block-image size-full">![](https://www.anexperimentwithoutscotch.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Screen-Shot-2022-01-28-at-8.21.34-AM.png)</figure>
<p>This hangs forever. A couple of times, a reboot of the instance seemed to fix it but this morning, nothing changed the behavior. So I decided to try to ssh from the terminal and lo and behold, this works. You have to download your private keys from your Lightsail account and then following <a href="https://lightsail.aws.amazon.com/ls/docs/en_us/articles/amazon-lightsail-ssh-using-terminal">these instructions</a> worked fine from the terminal. This will probably be my default going forward.</p>]]></content><author><name>Brett</name></author><category term="Technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog runs in Lightsail on WordPress with a Certified by Bitnami instance. Lately, I’ve run into the following when trying to ssh in from the Lightsail console:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Sovereignty of Good - Book Review</title><link href="http://brettbim.com/books/reviews/2022/01/22/the-sovereignty-of-good-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sovereignty of Good - Book Review" /><published>2022-01-22T12:24:10+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-22T12:24:10+00:00</updated><id>http://brettbim.com/books/reviews/2022/01/22/the-sovereignty-of-good-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://brettbim.com/books/reviews/2022/01/22/the-sovereignty-of-good-review.html"><![CDATA[<p>Iris Murdoch’s The Sovereignty of Good is perhaps her best known philosophical book. It consists of three essays focused on moral philosophy and her belief in a Platonic basis for it. I’ve had the book on my mega monopoly bookseller wishlist for quite awhile, probably when I read Mathew Crawford’s Shop Class as Soulcraft which frequently references Murdoch’s concepts of attention. My recent focus on ethical philosophy in Happiness, specifically Plato, prompted me to buy this book. It’s a short book, only 100 pages, and the three essays are straightforward to read.</p>

<p>The main theme of the book and essays is the concept of Good as the primary ideal of moral philosophy. The first essay, The Idea of Perfection, examines the state of moral philosophy in the mid to late 20th century from Kant to the behaviorists to the existentialists to the most recent movements in analytic philosophy. None of these schools have a rich and nuanced concept of moral philosophy. Each school drives out the self in a variety of ways: Kant via Reason, Existentialism through the removal of intrinsic meaning defined by an external source, etc. Our removal of the self and its messiness along with science’s influences on society in moving away from God means that moral philosophy is reduced to thinking goodness and morality are functions of our will and not some externally existing ‘thing’. We choose what is good based on the freedom of our will and that is that. Additionally, we move away from the idea of virtue and towards a concept of “right”. We no longer ask “What is Good?”. Instead, we ask “What is Right?” which biases us towards a materialistic, false scientism when it comes to moral philosophy.</p>

<p>Murdoch strongly disagrees with these concepts and instead presents a moral philosophy based on a transcendent Good that is undefinable but still clearly exists external to our will for us to focus on. This makes our materialistic, technocratic selves quite uncomfortable in an age where everything supposedly has a reason and must be measured for its efficiency. But if we examine our lived experience and lean on common sense, it seems true that the Good really does exist even if we can’t quite put our fingers on what it is. Her debt to Plato and the Allegory of the Cave is clear here.</p>

<p>Murdoch argues for a much richer inner life than do her contemporaries or immediate philosophical ancestors. This inner life is “hazy” as she puts it and not subject to measurements or efficiencies. Contemporary moral philosophy judges every thing on actions: we have no way to inspect the inner life Murdoch treasures and therefore can only decide whether a person is moral by his or her actions. Murdoch argues this is far too limiting to develop a rich, moral philosophy and instead that our inner life can (and DOES!) contain much more. This lines up with most people’s simple common sense beliefs about their “self”.</p>

<p>Murdoch’s example involves M and D, two women associated via the marriage of D to M’s son. M behaves towards D flawlessly (her external visible actions) but internally, she believes that D is simple and plain and below her son. Over time, M’s vision of D comes to change. She sees that her son loves D, that perhaps instead of simple, D is carefree and happy, etc. Her actions have never changed but her morality has in that it has grown along a continuum. Modern moral philosophy has no mechanism with which to judge this example because there are no actions that have changed. M’s actions are the same yet something has changed. This is why Murdoch argues for concepts beyond the examination of actions that behaviorism and existentialism focus on. Most people would likely agree with her that there does seem to be some rich inner life and that a moral philosophy that does not account for this life is suspect.</p>

<p>This also has implications for concepts like Freedom. In the existentialist/behaviorist view, Freedom is the will making its moral choices often divorced from any anchor in reality. For Murdoch and a theory of Good, Freedom is the choices made on a progressive continuum towards Perfection. It is not random free choice. In other words, M chose to look more carefully, to attend more clearly, to D’s characteristics and her son’s love for D. M had the Freedom to choose whether to do this but once she chose it, her path was set moving her forward towards an idea of Perfection, e.g. constantly improving via choice one’s understanding of something, in this case the personality of her daughter-in-law.</p>

<p>This idea of Perfection and constant movement on the continuum towards it is fundamental to Murdoch’s philosophy. By conceiving of a transcendent Good and then attending to it, we grow more moral over time. This is in sharp contrast to the materialistic view of existentialism where everything is based on external actions and there is no historical context, e.g. no continuum, within which to judge the morality of an agent. It’s also important to note Murdoch’s concept of attention. For her, morality comes via attention to reality, the real world (the relationship M’s son has with D for example) and then fitting ones decisions and beliefs around that. By contrast, in existentialism, the will operates independent from reality leaving one’s morality to be developed in a void. This is a slippery slope towards “things that are right for you aren’t right for me”. Only by judging moral philosophy on its connection to reality can we have standards that we once derived from the Divine.</p>

<p>Murdoch’s idea of Perfection requires the governance of reality as a guide for growth in a moral way. We must attend to what we experience, our relationships, our impacts on the environment, etc so that we can develop our moral philosophy towards better actions. Reality comes first, then growth towards the Good, then actions unlike the existentialists and behaviorists for whom actions are the genesis of moral philosophy. For them, actions are everything. But for Plato and Murdoch and Aquinas among others, the genesis of moral philosophy is a transcendent Good (for Aquinas, this was God as primary, for the others the Good is primary on its own) towards which we apply attention first that enables actions. The Good is contextual, it has a history to which we must attend and this is how it differs dramatically from the existentialist/behaviorist view with its isolated will.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Iris Murdoch’s The Sovereignty of Good is perhaps her best known philosophical book. It consists of three essays focused on moral philosophy and her belief in a Platonic basis for it. I’ve had the book on my mega monopoly bookseller wishlist for quite awhile, probably when I read Mathew Crawford’s Shop Class as Soulcraft which frequently references Murdoch’s concepts of attention. My recent focus on ethical philosophy in Happiness, specifically Plato, prompted me to buy this book. It’s a short book, only 100 pages, and the three essays are straightforward to read.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Happiness – Epicurus, Seneca, and Augustine</title><link href="http://brettbim.com/2022/01/11/on-happiness-epicurus-seneca-and-augustine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Happiness – Epicurus, Seneca, and Augustine" /><published>2022-01-11T13:13:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-11T13:13:09+00:00</updated><id>http://brettbim.com/2022/01/11/on-happiness-epicurus-seneca-and-augustine</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://brettbim.com/2022/01/11/on-happiness-epicurus-seneca-and-augustine/"><![CDATA[<p>This is part of a stop and start series summarizing the writings in <em><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/796741.Happiness?from_search=true&amp;from_srp=true&amp;qid=TXzE6O7fPJ&amp;rank=1">Happiness – Classic and Contemporary Readings in Philosophy</a></em>. You can read other parts of the series starting <a href="https://www.anexperimentwithoutscotch.com/2021/10/30/on-happiness-a-blog-post-series-maybe/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Today’s third installment is a summary of what the Stoics represented by Seneca and Augustine felt about happiness. The Stoics have in recent years returned to popularity, largely through the writings of Ryan Holiday. Stoicism was in direct competition for mind share and pupils with Epicureans during the ancient world. The writing of Seneca in this book is in response to the core Epicurean belief that pleasure is the highest good. Seneca believes Virtue is the higher good. Seneca’s main argument with Epicurean philosophy is not that it is necessarily bad but that it is far too easy to fall into a vicious cycle when pursuing happiness via pleasure.</p>

<p>According to Seneca, Virtue is the highest good and has the added benefit of providing some pleasure. The analogy he uses is like the field plowed for corn that then allows some flowers to bloom around its borders, Virtue allows for pleasure to bloom in small ways as well. The benefit of Virtue is that it allows man to stand up to the tribulations of life whereas pleasure does not. As someone who struggles with things like carbs and Twitter, I can attest to pleasure largely being weak and fleeting.</p>

<p>Interestingly, Epicurus, while having a totally materialistic metaphysical basis for his philosophy, did not advocate for the gluttony that we typically associate with his philosophy. Much of what Epicurus said was directed at developing a freedom of fear, both of the gods and of man, and directing one’s life to learning via our senses. This then allowed man to acquire pleasure though still in some moderation. As so often with philosophical leaders, it was later adherents to the philosophy who bastardized the concepts.</p>

<p>Seneca advocated for Virtue being the standard bearer for our direction in life and that by doing so, man would be able to both acquire pleasure (via higher goods like learning and philosophical development) and to withstand all the things that buffet and attack our happiness and equilibrium in life. Virtue allows us to be free from suffering because we know that our actions have truth. Virtue is independent of Fortune. One can lead a virtuous life filled with truth and wisdom while remaining poverty stricken but a rich man whose happiness is based on his pleasures can be stripped of them by Fortune. Virtue places man beyond the grasp of desire which means he achieves freedom via being virtuous. This is not unlike the ideas of Iris Murdoch who talks about freedom not as an independent thing in a laissez-faire will but a result of the consequences of a framework for action. In other words, by striving towards Virtue (or Perfection for Murdoch), we gain freedom from the whims and baseness of pleasure.</p>

<p>Seneca says “We have been born under a monarchy; to obey God is freedom.” This is a much deeper definition of freedom (and a seemingly paradoxical one to the modern mind) than one we operate in today where we are bombarded by people yelling about freedoms to not wear a mask or the freedom to develop a cryptocurrency or other “freedoms” based on an independent will that is largely nihilistic in nature. This freedom is hard to comprehend when one has been immersed in the cultural idea of individual freedom as the highest good. Our cultural idea of freedom is totally independent choice. However, Seneca believed that this led to base desires ruling man’s life and that true freedom came from a structural metaphysic based on virtue. Only in this path would we gain true freedom from those base desires like gluttony and greed. As Jerzy Gregorek has said, “Easy choices, hard life. Hard choices, easy life.” Today’s definition of freedom (and happiness) are entirely of the first time. But Seneca (and in some ways Epicurus and more so Augustine) believed freedom came from the latter.</p>

<p>Interestingly, something that is not regularly talked about is that Seneca believed Virtue came from God, that we had a sacred obligation to <strong>be human</strong>, e.g. not be bothered by those things which affects us because we are not divine. This relates him to Augustine in some ways who had similar thoughts. Augustine’s core moral was Wisdom which came from God. Wisdom is the opposite of want or more accurately, frees one from want much as Seneca believe Virtue freed us from the spiral of pleasure seeking. Wisdom for Augustine was the measure of the soul, that it kept the soul in equilibrium and prevented that same spiral into pleasure seeking behavior. Wisdom requires a constant seeking (which interestingly ties back to Murdoch’s ideas in The Sovereignty of Good) and therefore, we are never deemed “wise”, only that we are constantly trying to increase our wisdom.</p>

<p>The way to wisdom for Augustine was through moderation, that want (of pleasures or riches) pulls us away from wisdom which is defined as seeking God. Again, as with Seneca and later, Murdoch, Happiness is derived via our pursuit of something less concrete than basic pleasures and our ability to improve or increase that pursuit over time. Happiness is not derived from the acquisition of things but from the acquisition of wisdom. Things can be a means to this (I bought a guitar during the pandemic, the purchase of which provided a tiny bit of impermanent happiness) by allowing us to develop wisdom (playing the guitar and increasing my abilities provides a constant stream of happiness). But it is key for both Seneca and Augustine that it is not the materialistic thing itself, it is what it provides on the path to wisdom. If I had to sell the guitar to make rent, I could still sing as a way to improve musical abilities.</p>

<p>To me, Seneca and Augustine have a very similar view of Happiness and its providence. I’ve read far more Stoic philosophy than I have that of Augustine but I’m interested in branching out further into his beliefs. Next up is Thomas Aquinas who believed happiness came from the contemplation of God.</p>]]></content><author><name>Brett</name></author><category term="Philosophy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is part of a stop and start series summarizing the writings in Happiness – Classic and Contemporary Readings in Philosophy. You can read other parts of the series starting here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Old Sabine WMA Deer Hunt</title><link href="http://brettbim.com/2021/12/19/old-sabine-wma-deer-hunt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Old Sabine WMA Deer Hunt" /><published>2021-12-19T12:55:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-19T12:55:00+00:00</updated><id>http://brettbim.com/2021/12/19/old-sabine-wma-deer-hunt</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://brettbim.com/2021/12/19/old-sabine-wma-deer-hunt/"><![CDATA[<p>Finding myself with time to spare lately, I did my first standby hunt through the Texas Parks &amp; Wildlife system this past week at Old Sabine WMA near Lindale. Earlier this year, with much less time on my hands, I forgot to apply for any of the gun deer permits so standby became my only option. Luckily, I was the only one to show up Wednesday morning and got my choice of remaining spots in the hunt.</p>

<p>The Old Sabine hunt is a good one. The biologists and employees are helpful and considerate. In most years, they actually have a cookout the first night for all the hunters which is a first in my experience with draw hunts. Unfortunately, Covid has changed protocols and they were unable to do that this year. Still, they offer to teach people how to field dress game, they’ll come help you track and get anything you shoot out of the woods and they do their best to make sure you have a good experience.</p>

<p>This hunt this year occurred at a pretty bad time (full moon) and the weather was atrocious for hunting with high winds, highs in the mid 70s and overnight temps in the high 60s. More like surfing weather than hunting weather. While there isn’t much you can do about the weather, one thing I learned for the future even on draw hunts is to cross-reference the lunar cycles and try to avoid full moons. When it’s as bright as it was this weekend, deer and hogs are far more nocturnal and move very little during shooting hours.</p>

<p>I choose compartment 4 which is on the far west end of the 5700 acre area. I had done some reading and thought there might be more hogs there. My compartment was 241 acres with a little bit of river border but mostly just large, bottom land hardwood. We’ve been rather dry here which meant it was difficult to find sign or tracks. I ended up setting up the in a semi-clearing that separated some large timber areas from a slough. I’d seen some game trails going back and forth and thought they might use the clearing to move into the woods to feed. I had brought both my climbing stand and popup blind. However, given the density of the brush and forest on the WMA, the popup was mostly useless. I spent all my time in the climber.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, no deer or hogs agreed with my plan. Over the course of the 2 days and 4 sits, I didn’t see anything larger than a squirrel. Compounding the heat and full moon problem, just getting in carrying the stand and basic gear resulted in me sweating like a feral pig because of the heat and humidity which didn’t help matters. Still, it wasn’t just me as the hunters in the compartment next to mine that I talked to in the evenings saw nothing the whole weekend too. In fact, nothing was shot the entire time by anyone on the hunt, 15 or so hunters. In talking to the biologists afterwards, about half of the drawn hunters left before the hunt was over. This is another key lesson of these hunts. People often quit before the hunt is over. If you think there is another compartment you’d like to try, it’s worth asking the TPWD folks if you can switch.</p>

<p>Overall, it was a good time to be in the woods even with all the adversity. Mostly a lot of bad luck with the weather which was pretty unexpected for December. Of course, the day the hunt was over, a big cold front came through with some rain, making this weekend perfect hunting weather. Such is life. I ended up walking a lot of compartment four and found an old fish camp. The shack is sitting on top of an old Coleman pop up camper. It’s interesting to think about what it was like 30-40 years ago. Who went to the trouble of building those shacks out in the woods just to fish a muddy river? The property was acquired by TPWD in 1994 so they are all pretty run down now.</p>

<p>This is probably the end of my hunting season though there’s an outside chance I could get up to Arkansas and try to take a deer on my in-laws property. Deer season ends in a few weeks and I don’t think I’ll have a chance to get back out in Texas. I did two draw hunts this year, one squirrel and this one at Old Sabine. I also hunted dove 3 times on public leases near Bonham. I got out more this year than in previous years so I’m happy about that.</p>

<p><a href="https://recorder.google.com/share/a5ac5dee-94d4-4f0f-8195-87f9d0e8e614">Recording of two wrens talking to each other Friday morning</a></p>

<figure class="wp-block-gallery columns-3 is-cropped wp-block-gallery-11 is-layout-flex">- <figure>![](https://www.anexperimentwithoutscotch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/PXL_20211215_161857746-768x1024.jpg)</figure>
- <figure>![](https://www.anexperimentwithoutscotch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/PXL_20211215_220550234-1024x768.jpg)</figure>
- <figure>![](https://www.anexperimentwithoutscotch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/PXL_20211215_220604959-768x1024.jpg)</figure>
- <figure>![](https://www.anexperimentwithoutscotch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/PXL_20211217_155911072-768x1024.jpg)</figure>

</figure>]]></content><author><name>Brett</name></author><category term="Hunting" /><category term="Outdoors" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Finding myself with time to spare lately, I did my first standby hunt through the Texas Parks &amp; Wildlife system this past week at Old Sabine WMA near Lindale. Earlier this year, with much less time on my hands, I forgot to apply for any of the gun deer permits so standby became my only option. Luckily, I was the only one to show up Wednesday morning and got my choice of remaining spots in the hunt.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Happiness – Plato Edition</title><link href="http://brettbim.com/2021/11/18/on-happiness-plato-edition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Happiness – Plato Edition" /><published>2021-11-18T12:56:24+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-18T12:56:24+00:00</updated><id>http://brettbim.com/2021/11/18/on-happiness-plato-edition</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://brettbim.com/2021/11/18/on-happiness-plato-edition/"><![CDATA[<p>This is the second in a series of posts on readings from <em><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/796741.Happiness?from_search=true&amp;from_srp=true&amp;qid=TXzE6O7fPJ&amp;rank=1">Happiness: Classic and Contemporary Readings in Philosophy</a></em>. The series start is <a href="https://www.anexperimentwithoutscotch.com/2021/10/30/on-happiness-a-blog-post-series-maybe/">here</a> along with an index if you are interested in others.</p>

<p>The first reading from the book is from Plato’s <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_(Plato)">The Republic</a></em> and includes Books II, IV and IX. The selected readings are concerned with justice and whether or not it is a good in and of itself or if instead, as Glaucon argues, merely something irksome like gymnastics practice that we ascribe to for its results only. Said another way, should justice be something we aspire to do or have like feelings of enjoyment or is justice something we do only because of compulsion? Glaucon and his brother argue that it is the latter, that given the opportunity to be unjust without consequence, man would invariably choose to do so in the same way man would choose to avoid other disciplines aimed at the future over the present.</p>

<p>Plato via Socrates believes the opposite, that justice is an end, not a means and that man, being separate from the animals based on his rational capacity, will choose to be just in the same way he would choose to be happy. Plato supports his argument by discussing the rational principle versus the appetitive principle in man. He does this utilizing the emotion anger in an interesting way. Initially, Glaucon thinks that anger belongs to the appetitive or irrational side of man. But Plato points out that we are never angry with ourselves when we are overindulging or being unjust, only after the fact. Spirit, this lion that resides in us, is separate from both the appetitive impulses and the rational man.</p>

<p>These three concepts (appetitive, the lion that represents the spirited side, and the rational) make up the whole man. Glaucon is arguing for a mixture where the appetitive and the spirited would reign supreme while the rational would be weak and ineffective, e.g. someone who was wholly unjust while appearing to be just on the outside. Socrates argues that happiness comes from having the rational man as the strongest principle and that the other two occur in moderation.</p>

<p>Whether one sides with Glaucon or Socrates here seems to boil down to one’s fundamental belief about how man derives happiness from existence. On one hand, the picture is that of selfish greed, excess consumption and the immediate. This is a pessimistic view of humanity, a precursor to nihilism where nothing matters at all. On the other, rationality holds the stronger hand and that by keeping appetites in check, happiness is increased because then the higher goals of justice and meaningful pleasure via philosophy can be achieved.</p>

<p>In today’s world, we are surrounded by appeals to our animal nature, far more than anything Glaucon could have imagined. Consumerism and consumption is THE portrayed ideal whether it’s through acquiring more thing or drowning ourselves in the incessant fire hose of information from social media and the internet. We have become gluttons for these things because they are easier and closer to the appetitive principles in our animal nature. To achieve true happiness, Plato would likely have advised us to keep this in check and turn towards our rational side. Is the thing in the path you are striving for what’s important for happiness or is it the path itself? This shift changes how we value things and lessens the disappointment when we do not achieve the “thing” we were focused on.</p>

<p>The appetitive side will always lead to short term happiness and long term disappointment. We can only eat Cheetohs for dinner for so long before the effects are felt. This goes for any other concrete thing we might strive for from a new car to a promotion to a ranch. Far better, as the Stoics have taught, to curb the appetites and be satisfied with what we have, turning the energy we had focused on the short term achievement towards the underlying mechanisms that provide those achievements.</p>

<p>In the end, Plato advised us that happiness comes not from the immediate but from the movement towards perfection of an ideal. This also had the fortunate side effect of building a better society at the same time, something our consumerist culture should take note of. Strengthening our rational side while taming the appetitive side with the spirit’s help will lead to a happier, more meaningful life that avoids the ups and downs that come from indulging our immediate tendencies.</p>

<p>As always, if you’ve liked this post or others, you can <a href="https://www.anexperimentwithoutscotch.com/subscribe/">sign up to be notified</a> whenever I write something new. On average, this happens about 1-2 times a month so it definitely won’t clog your inbox.</p>]]></content><author><name>Brett</name></author><category term="Philosophy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is the second in a series of posts on readings from Happiness: Classic and Contemporary Readings in Philosophy. The series start is here along with an index if you are interested in others.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Zeno’s Migration and Tech Leadership</title><link href="http://brettbim.com/2021/11/15/on-zenos-migration-and-tech-leadership/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Zeno’s Migration and Tech Leadership" /><published>2021-11-15T13:19:23+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-15T13:19:23+00:00</updated><id>http://brettbim.com/2021/11/15/on-zenos-migration-and-tech-leadership</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://brettbim.com/2021/11/15/on-zenos-migration-and-tech-leadership/"><![CDATA[<figure class="wp-block-image size-full">![](https://www.anexperimentwithoutscotch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Screen-Shot-2021-11-03-at-5.46.04-AM.png)<figcaption>Zeno’s Migration</figcaption></figure>
<p>Jean Yang, founder of Akita Software, has been talking on Twitter lately about the chasm between the technical “guidance” from large tech firms like Netflix and Amazon and what your average, run-of-the-mill tech firm does in the wild. I’ve started calling this latter group, a much larger cohort than the former, “small tech” loosely defined as 10-50ish engineering types. This idea of Zeno’s Migration, a riff on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeno%27s_paradoxes">Zeno’s Paradoxes</a> for those who slept through their classics courses, is full of promise like the Dichotomy paradox that says because a journey is a set infinite steps, it can’t even begin much less end which is especially apropos of many small tech companies cloud migration plan.</p>

<p>The idea here is that in order to complete a migration, you have to travel halfway an infinite number of times. The constant refrain from technical leadership is that next quarter we’re going to be “X” farther along the journey on the migration de jour. This migration often involves shiny, jangly technology choices like “rewrite the front end in React” or “migrate everything to the cloud”. Unfortunately, this constant refrain ignores hard strategic realities on the ground where a small tech firm has serious limitations in what it can accomplish. In an ideal world, free of harsh realities, these constraints would be manageable. Alas, there are no ideal worlds.</p>

<p>I think the problem arises because the pervasive definitional concept in our industry is “The Project”. When everything is a project, it sets up incentive conflicts in priority determination. In an organization that is highly typical in the industry where “the business” and “technology” are considered different entities, the migration is always a project defined and defended by “technology” which puts it at odds with other projects defined by “the business”. Even at organizations that nominally follow a more product based organizational structure, the key concept is projects involving kickoffs and planning and story writing and infinite other steps. As with most systems, the focus at this level is too granular and misses the forest for the trees.</p>

<p>A more holistic solution is to step back at least one level in the system to “The Team” and assess the situation there. The product team becomes the atomic unit of measure, not the project. This requires a shift in thinking and language but when done correctly, Zeno’s Migration melts away in the same way Zeno’s Paradoxes do because we shift from a discrete function with a start and an end to an infinite series (the outcomes and measurements of the team on a continual improvement cycle ala DevOps philosophy). In this model, a cloud migration just becomes part of the continual improvement process.</p>

<p>This still raises the question of when to do such things. With limited resources, even a well organized product team needs guardrails on what to focus on. This is where organizational technical leadership can provide value with written visions and <a href="https://lethain.com/good-engineering-strategy-is-boring/">strategies</a>. In tandem with these strategies, it’s critical to have metrics measured in outcomes that are regularly reviewed and publicized to the broader organization. These strategies should be cyclical in nature, e.g. they do not have an end but define measurements like “we will migrate X services per quarter or half”. Without these strategies defined and monitored for outcomes, even well organized product teams in the typical technology business will fail to do this migration work because it’s too easy for it to fall on the floor.</p>

<p>A corollary to Zeno’s Migration that I’ve seen and heard a lot is the lift and shift strategy of cloud migration. An organization, hearing that “the cloud is the future” or whatever, moves (or more often pays some consulting firm to move) their entire operation to the cloud with the idea and promise that this allows the architecture to then move to a more cloud native form over time without having to migrate where the services live.</p>

<p>Of course, this achieves none of the benefits of a cloud native architecture and moves all of the existing maladaptive processes along with it. But returning to “The Project” as atomic unit, this is easy to reason about, define and measure. I think there is also often an unstated concept here that technology leadership maintains related to cost and incentives. Over time, as subsidies and cost breaks expire, running an org in the cloud just like you did on prem is likely to be much more expensive. The idea is that at that point, it would be easy to explain to the business how a rewrite or rearchitecture will save money which is always the easiest metric to measure.</p>

<p>There are two things going on here, one part sociological and one part technical (which is convenient since these are all sociotechnical systems). The sociological part involves humans tendency to look at achievement as An End. When we look at greatness, we think of a finished thing and not as something that happens to just be quite far along the continuum of that particular thing. The second issue is that in order to deal with the continuum of technical growth and improvement, we need to have a way to move successfully from vision to tactics which is what Richard Rumelt calls <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/1709397.Richard_P_Rumelt">Strategy</a>. We must define the problem, the constraint and actions required to solve the problem. This helps identify tradeoffs and things we cannot do in order to achieve the vision. This is where good technical leadership shines brightest and is often missing from existing tech growth plans.</p>

<p>In the end, I think technical growth is contextual. A team of 30 engineers can’t read a paper from Netflix and apply it to their situation. Leadership must analyze the existing context for opportunity and then define strategies for that opportunity that define the problem to be solved and the actions that will be taken (or not taken which is a critical part of strategy) to succeed. Then the strategy must be publicized and monitored for progress along its continuum. As growth occurs, the strategy and context should be revisited for modifications as necessary. This is all hard management work that in my experience is difficult to develop and nurture. There are systems involved here with first order incentives that are easier to both talk about and create that work against the harder second order incentives to dig into the history and context of a given situation and create solutions specifically for it. Until technical leadership as an industry is better at thinking about these systems, we’ll continue to read shiny new ideas from large tech organizations and try to pound that round object into the square hole we are dealing with.</p>]]></content><author><name>Brett</name></author><category term="Technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[![](https://www.anexperimentwithoutscotch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Screen-Shot-2021-11-03-at-5.46.04-AM.png)Zeno’s Migration Jean Yang, founder of Akita Software, has been talking on Twitter lately about the chasm between the technical “guidance” from large tech firms like Netflix and Amazon and what your average, run-of-the-mill tech firm does in the wild. I’ve started calling this latter group, a much larger cohort than the former, “small tech” loosely defined as 10-50ish engineering types. This idea of Zeno’s Migration, a riff on Zeno’s Paradoxes for those who slept through their classics courses, is full of promise like the Dichotomy paradox that says because a journey is a set infinite steps, it can’t even begin much less end which is especially apropos of many small tech companies cloud migration plan.]]></summary></entry></feed>